Mattia Amadio

Climate and disaster risk specialist

I am an environmental scientist with 10 years of experience in the field of climate-affected hazards and disaster risk management. I have been involved in academic research projects over multiple countries, working with highly-ranked

In 2010 I was awarded a PhD in Science and Management of Climate Change from the Ca' Foscari University of Venice.

Since 2012 I work as consultant for the World Bank's GFDRR. My expertise covers geo-analytics and mapping, impact modelling and climate change. I am a science enthusiast with a skeptical attitude.





mattia.amadio@gmail.com

+39 3488441401



Venice, Italy



bit.ly/disasterologist

WORK EXPERIENCE

Short-term consultant

GFDRR, World Bank

2018 – Present

Washington DC (US)

- Climate and Disaster risk analytics (CDDR)
- o Geodata review and management (ThinkHazard!; GFDRR GeoNode; Risk Data Library)
- Risk Data Library design and development
- Support to DRR projects

Contact: Pierre Chrzanowski

Asian Development Bank

2021 - Present

Manila (PH)

o Development of Climate and Disaster Risk screening and assessment tool

Contact: Charles A. Rodgers; Belinda Hewitt

Academic researcher

Euro-Mediterranean Centre on Climate Change

Research foundation on climate change

- Climate-KIC project SAFERPLACES, flash-flood hazard from extreme precipitations and risk mitigation in European cities (2 years)
- H2020 project CLARA, climate forecast enabled knowledge services (3 years)
- ECHO project CHAKE OU, flood risk mapping in Paraguay (8
- National Climate Change Adaptation Plan (PNACC) for Italy (2 years)

Contact: Jaroslav Mysiak

SKILLS

Spatial analytics

Map Design

Python

Geodata management

LANGUAGES

English	Italian	Spanish
Full Professional	Native Proficiency	Elementary Proficiency
Proficiency		

LATEST PUBLICATIONS

12/2021

Journal article

Cost-benefit analysis of coastal flood defence measures in the North Adriatic Sea

M. Amadio, A.H. Essenfelder, S. Bagli, S. Marzi et al.

Natural Hazards and Earth System Sciences

Cost-benefit analysis of coastal flood defence infrastructures in Italy considering the effects of climate change.

2021

Study report

Investment in Disaster Risk Management in Europe makes economic sense

GFDRR, ECA

The World Bank

Reporting for DG-ECHO on Cost-Benefit analysis of existing DRM projects in the EU.

Study report

Disasters, Conflict, and Displacement: Intersectional **Risks in South Sudan**

GFDRR, IOM

The World Bank

Part one: analytic mapping of intersectional risks for South Sudan based on existing data and assessments related to natural hazards and conflict and fragility.

03/2019

Journal article

Testing empirical and synthetic flood damage models: the case of Italy

M. Amadio, A.R. Scorzini, F. Carisi, A.H. Essenfelder et al.

Natural Hazards and Earth System Sciences

Study to evaluate the predictive performance of existing flood damage models in comparison with empirical losses.

EDUCATION

PhD in Science and Management of Climate Change

Ca' Foscari University

09/2015 - 12 / 2018

Venice (IT)

o Thesis title: Integrated Framework for Flood Risk Assessment in Italy. The thesis consists of four articles published on academic journals.